Finding aid for Jean Sanville papers SSC.MS.00275
Sophia Smith Collection
Jean Sanville papers
1951-2005
Sophia Smith Collection
Sanville, Jean
SSC.MS.00275
30.25 linear feet (27 boxes. Other materials in the collection: 1 OS box.)
Jean Bovard Sanville was one of the country's first social workers to establish a full-time private practice. A longtime member of the faculty of the Smith College of Social Work, she was regarded as a groundbreaker in many aspects of her profession, including education. The Jean Sanville papers contain correspondence; speeches and other writings; teaching materials; conference materials; and organization files. The bulk of the collection consists of material relating to Sanville's professional life, particularly papers developed for presentation at courses, conventions, conferences, seminars and workshops. There are also book reviews and commentaries on other people's work
Biographical Note
Jean Bovard Sanville was one of the country's first social workers to enter full-time private practice. Sanville was born in 1918. She graduated from the University of Colorado in 1940. After graduating from the Smith College School for Social Work in 1942 and earning her doctorate from the International College in California, she worked in various mental health agencies. In 1958 she broke new ground in her profession, entering full-time private practice. She was also an innovator in education for clinical practice. Sanville was Visiting Professor at the UCLA School of Social Welfare, and founder and first dean of the Institute for Clinical Social Work. She was co-founder and training analyst at the Los Angeles Society for Psycholanalytic Studies. Sanville served on the faculty of the Smith School for Social Work Program of Continuing Education since 1984. She was editor of the Clinical Social Work Journal and has written many scholarly papers and articles. Sanville often collaborated with her husband, Joel Shor. She died in 2013.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were donated by Jean Sanville. In addition to those listed in Related Accessions, there were seven accessions between 1991 and 1997: 91S-55 and six others.
Conditions Governing Access
These papers are available to researchers on a process-on-demand basis. Therefore, there are potentially closed materials, such as case histories and student files, in all boxes. There are closed materials in boxes related to accessions 01S-31, 03S-25 and, possibly, others.
Scope and Contents
The Jean Sanville papers contain correspondence; speeches and other writings; teaching materials; conference materials; and organization files. The bulk of the collection consists of material relating to Sanville's professional life, particularly papers developed for presentation at courses, conventions, conferences, seminars and workshops. There are also book reviews and commentaries on other people's work, as well as documents pertaining to Sanville's long-term involvement with the Los Angeles Institute and Society for Psychoanalytic Studies (LAISPS).
Adolescent psychology--United States--History--Sources; Child psychology--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Psychiatric social work--History--Sources; Social work education--United States--History--Sources; Clinical child psychology--History--Sources; Sanville, Jean; correspondence; articles; syllabi; Speeches; Writings; lecture notes; Organization files; reports; Awards; Diaz, Ralph Morton
- Jean Sanville professional correspondence, essays and materials related to professional organizations and conferences, 1981-2005; 2005-S-0012; Sanville, Jean; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Emails and other correspondence, 1997-2003; 2005-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - University of Cambridge clippings, memoranda, fliers, 1981; 2005-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - Conference materials on alcoholism in Soviet Union, 1975-1982; 2005-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - John R. Seeley essays, undated; 2005-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - Daycare notes, questionnaires, related correspondence, 1982; 2005-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous fliers and memoranda, 1998-2005; 2005-S-0012 (Box 2)
  - Gail Sisson Steger essay, undated; 2005-S-0012 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Psychoanalysis correspondence, memoranda, essays, miscellaneous materials, 1992-2001; 2005-S-0012 (Box 2)
  - California Society for Clinical Social work correspondence and miscellaneous materials, 1995-2003; 2005-S-0012 (Box 2)
  - Los Angeles Institute and Society for Psychoanalytic Studies correspondence, articles, miscellaneous materials, 2002-2004; 2005-S-0012 (Box 2)
- Jean Sanville professional and personal writings and miscellaneous materials, 1974-2005; 2006-S-0020; Sanville, Jean; 1.25 linear feet (1 box)
  - Correspondence, 1981-2005; 2006-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Agenda, minutes, other materials related to professional associations, 1974-2005; 2006-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Sanville materials related to courses and workshops, 1970-1982; 2006-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Sanville real estate materials including leases and contracts, 1995-2002; 2006-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Writings by Sanville and others, 1985-1996; 2006-S-0020 (Box 1)
  - Publications, brochures, fliers related to personal and professional interests, 1990-2005; 2006-S-0020 (Box 1)
- Jean Sanville professional papers, teaching materials, awards, 1956-2006; 2014-S-0072; Sanville, Jean; 2 linear feet (3 boxes)
  General
  Jean Sanville died in 2013; this appears to be the last of her materials.
  Conditions Governing Access
  - Teaching materials, licenses, articles, drafts, 1956-2005; 2014-S-0072 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript drafts, 1999-2004; 2014-S-0072 (Box 2)
  - Copies of four Sanville books, 1978-2003; 2014-S-0072 (Box 2)
  - Plaques and awards, 1979-1995; 2014-S-0072 (Box 3)